all right hello and welcome everyone
this is active inference guest stream
83.1 here with Susan Hasty and our guest
Simon wordley so Susan will say a few
words that will lead us in Simon has
many resources prepared and exciting
perspectives to share so thank you both
for joining Susan to you
okay are you ready for me go for it
awesome okay thank you so much Simon I
was been looking so forward to uh to
introducing you to the active inference
Community um and uh in Wordly mapping uh
and what you have been able to um
accomplish
and you know it is
is amazing how much
admiration um that uh that people have
shown you there and so I'm gonna just
I'm gonna I'm British you can't do this
to me you can't do this to
me we're not American so is that you
know that actually there's a connection
between being the most strategic
Brilliant Minds that people know and the
humility you bring to it along with the
uh the jovial it's a cultural thing so
then we are so I turn it over turn it
over and and but we would like to I
would like to you to share how you came
about um you know the the um moving from
the you the experts on the stage to how
do you how did you tap into the need for
Bly mapping what was that where did that
where did that arise from well well it
was obviously some Fine Day in the UK
and I was sitting down there with my
enormous mind uh thinking about these
problems and and naturally the pure
Genius of myself I I no no it was
complete random accidents and everything
else I had got a clue what I was doing
so I um I was running a compy at the
time um and uh well actually I've got a
I've got some slides and give you a bit
of the the sort of formal history I can
show you the horror of it if you wish um
can you Daniel is it possible for me to
show my slides thank you very much uh so
I'm not going to go through this whole
it's 127 slide deck I'm not going to do
that I mean um uh but what I will do is
just talk about a couple so I'm going to
talk about the origin of mapping
and then we'll get on to I may as well
explain what a map is what it isn't and
then I'll mention a little bit about
patterns and then we've got these other
topics change gameplay how you identify
value but rather we won't go down that
path we'll we'll get into a a different
style of conversation I can show you
something called Meo and um because
Susan you are part of my education Group
which I really really appreciated way um
helping us map out that space
so let's start with the origin since you
asked me that question um this is
company called Fango uh that I used to
work for I got a photo this of the
website go see the CEO um and it was a
very uh sort of successful company at
the time uh very very profitable uh
rapidly growing uh but it had a problem
and that that problem was the CEO uh the
fat cat in charge had absolutely no idea
uh what they were doing they were just
making it up uh I mean um they were
totally and utterly clueless and I know
this for a fact because I was the CEO I
mean I I used to um come up with all
these wonderful statements about what
our future was uh so this is 2004 uh our
strategy as customer focus we will lead
an Innovative effort in the market
through our use of agile techniques and
open source uh become a leading provid
oh horrible but I literally pinched
these words uh from another company and
just changed a few things um and I I I
sort of was you know I had no idea what
I was doing I used to go around
listening to other CEOs talking about
strategy and I used to record all the
words they would say and I I started
aggregating these words and I called
these uh aggregations business level
abstractions of a healthy strategy or or
blahs for short and I used to publish
these common blah lists where things
like you know these are the words that
people are using digital disruptive
Innovative collaborative competitive
Advantage ecosystem open source Network
blah blah blah and so then what I did
was I created What's called the blah
template straty is blah we will lead a
blah effort of the market through our
use of blah and blah to build a Blah by
simply grab all these sorts of vision
statements and smashing them together
until I came up with a generalized
form and then I would just combine the
Blas and the blah templates uh to to
autogenerate strategies so uh you know
um last time I did this I created 64
things like this our strategy is
customer focus we will lead a
destructive effort of the market through
our use of innovative platforms and data
to build a collaborative ecosystem it
sounds it's complete garbage um but I
used to send these around to
people and I I get I get three basic
responses back uh which are the form
Well here here's another example our
strategy is innovative digital business
and we load a growth effort of the
market through our use of customer and I
can barely read it that is that painful
uh the three basic forms I used to get
back was this is the exact wording from
our business plan I've seen two of these
used already and my favorite one was aru
for
five which you know I didn't want to
tell the people but I just autogenerated
this garbage um so I was no idea at all
what I was doing completely clueless I
had done an NBA and of course I assumed
back in those days you learned all the
secrets of how to understand what a
business was is uh from doing an NBA I
now teaching um
couple of days here and there every year
at different Business Schools and I
realized the delusion that I had over
what you actually learned um so you know
I knew I was clueless I started to think
maybe other people were
struggling um a friend of mine by the
way if you ever want to I I don't think
it's available anymore this is a little
bit of an old presentation um he
actually cre just automated this there
was a uh lap that was built that would
would create you one of those generic
sort of it's much easier these days you
just go to chat GPT and just say give me
a strategy and it'll give you some
garbage and and you're away um so I
ended up reading every book I could find
I was getting
nowhere and by pure luck I I I was in a
a booksh shop in Ching cross in London
and I was talking to the Book seller and
I I was talking about all these straty
books I'd read and how none of them made
sense and she asked me had I ever read
um The Art of War by Sun Sue and I
hadn't and so she persuaded me being a
fantastic book seller to buy two
different versions of the book because
they're all
translations got to say I am so grateful
uh for that because it was in the
reading of the second version I noticed
a particular pan so sunu talked about
five factors that mattered in
competition now when we talk about
competition competition is the act of a
group of people seeking something um
whether it's knowledge resource or
whatever it happens to be and there are
many different forms of competition so
sometimes we will conflict with each
other that's we fight each other over
something sometimes we will cooperate
with each other so helping each other
sometimes we will uh collaborate so
laboring uh with each other so sometimes
fighting working or or or laboring so
those are multiple different forms of
competition uh they're all competition
they're all part the act and normally uh
we will possibly collaborate with one
group over here in order to cooperate
with another group over there in order
to conflict with another group over
there so you can have many many
different forms combinations of this I
often hear people talk try and create
new words for this I mean um um mostly
because they want competition just to
mean conflict and therefore they can
have different words like collaborate
which which is no no longer competition
because they Define competition as only
conflict and then cooperate and so then
they get to things well if we
collaborating and conflict but we don't
call it conflict we call it competition
we're co- competing collaborating and
then you get into these large horrible
spaghetti words just
meaningless it's really simple though
competition it's the act of seeking in
multiple groups and there multiple
different forms so when you look to the
um Sun su's work talk about five factors
that matter one have a purpose a moral
imperative to what you're trying to do
secondly understand the landscape that
you're competing in uh uh and then third
understand the climatic pain so the
heavens the weather so how the landscape
is changing and then you get into uh
principles of how you organize yourself
Doctrine and then you get into the sort
of gameplay and Leadership and I I was
like fascinated by this and then I came
across John Boyd the Mad major
uh famous for creating the UDA Loop and
so the first o of the UDA Loop is to
observe the environment so that's what
landscape and climactic patterns are
about or observation of a space then you
orientate yourself around the space
that's what principles are about and
then you need to decide where you're
going to act and this is where we get
into the game play and all those sorts
of leadership choices and at the heart
of this a fundamentally two WI the why
of purpose and the why of movement why
do I make this decision over over that
decision so this became for me the the
the you know the strategy cycle because
it sort of made sense uh you know I
remember I hadn't done the MBA so so I
didn't know the official things to talk
about and I got really fascinated by
this idea of observing the
landscape and so that's what brought me
into to Maps because I used to read
everything I could find on sort of
military history and one of my favorite
battles is the uh Battle of themop so
the ancient politicians well
um theistically ancient politician Greek
General had a problem
um they had the the Persians were
invading and we don't know quite the
number of Persians they're about 100
well we think somewhere between 100,000
to 70,000 roughly um and so the Greeks
were independent city states and the
mystically was I believe Athenian and so
what they decided to do was you know how
are we going to cope uh with this
Invasion force uh what they decided to
do was to block off the streets of
Artesia Force the Persians along a a
coastal Road into an nrow pass called
theropo uh where you know a small number
of TR could defend against a larger
force and in fact the number of troops
there there were about 4,000 Greeks
there and they were independent city
states but they they came together at
times um and within those 4,000 with 300
SPS and this is where we got the story
of the 300 from uh the 300 defending for
a considerable amount of time against a
much larger
Force now my fascination with this m was
was um I could use it as you know we
could use it as a way of discussing what
we're going to do what do we need to
move where do we need to defend uh who
do we need to work with it's a vehicle
for
communication and I started looking at
my own business and thinking about how
do we communicate and make decisions and
back in those days I was using something
called a swap diagram strengths
weaknesses opportunities threats be oh
fantastic you know um so I created a
SWAT diagram for this battle so strength
a well- trained Spartan Army a high
level of motivation not to become a
Persian slave weaknesses the e4s might
stop the Spartans turning up a truckload
of Persians are turning up opportunities
get rid of the Persians um and also get
rid of the Spartans where we happen to
be athenium we don't actually like the
Spartans as I say independent city
states uh and the threats and the
Persians get rid of us and the Oracle
says a really dodgy film might be
produced a few thousand years later
obviously added that one a bit
later um but I simply put these against
each other and I ask myself you know
what would you communicate and you know
use to communicate and determine
strategy in
battle and you know the same goes for
what would you do in saying competition
um you could either use position and
movement through an understanding of the
landscape that you're competing in or
you can use some sort of magic framework
like a swap just thinking well crank it
would be obvious you would try to
understand the landscape before you you
make a decision and here I was making
all these decisions using a magic
framework so at that point I said right
I need to understand the landscape that
my business is operating I need a
map I went looking for maps of uh
business and I couldn't find any um well
interestingly I can find well I found
lots of things called Maps so I I I
asked for example in my company
everybody to send me any Maps they had
and they said would send me loads like
things like systems Maps or business
process maps and mind maps and lots of
stuff like that but when I took one of
these maps and this is a map of uh
simple map of the uh online photo
service and I I looked at one component
CRM which stands for customer
relationship management and I simply
moved it across the screen but kept the
links the same so I went from there to
there and asked how has the map changed
but the answer is it hasn't changed and
for me that was immediately on OD
because I know if I take a geographical
map of the world and I take Australia
and put it next to the UK that has
fundamentally changed the meaning of the
map so why is the meaning of the map not
changed here well it's because it's not
a map it's a
graph and that's what all these maps
that I had had in common none of them
were Maps they were all graphs uh
business process graphs mind graphs
they're all nodes and connections
between nodes rather than maps of the
landscape so just to really spell that
out um these are uh three graphs uh and
they are identical there are three
places in the UK Nottingham London DOA
connected by two roads M1 M2 now the
thing about a graph all that really
matters in a graph is the nodes and the
connections and the waiting on the notes
that's it um the difference between that
and a map is
the reason why the three three maps at
the bottom are all completely different
while the three graphs at the top are
identical is the in a map space has
meaning you can't actually just move a
component without changing the
fundamental meaning of the map itself so
that's the distinction between a graph
and a map and everything I had which was
called a map was in fact a graph so I I
I sort of assumed at that point
well this must be what you learned at
NBA
schools um because obviously you learn
how to do the mapping and there are no
books on the subject uh so it must be
like really secretive and really
useful um or uh or or maybe completely
useless and have' been abandoned long
ago you I just sort of didn't know but
nonetheless I had no access to those
those resources so um and I couldn't
find any examples so I I thought well
I've somehow got to create a map so I
looked at a map and there basically
three components you need you need an in
order to give landscape the space
meaning you've got to have an anchor
such as magnetic north you've got to
have position of pieces so this is North
Southeast or west of that and then
you've got to have something known as
consistency of movement so if I'm going
north I'm going north I'm not going
south no sort of teleportation there's
got to be some sort of
consistency so um I thought right let's
try and map something and so I did and I
MA my business but I I'll show you a
t-shop only because my business bit was
bit dull and t- shops I find more
fascinating don't know why so what's my
Anor going to be so I thought well I'm
going to focus around the users and
immediately well who are the users I've
got my consumer
and I I've got the business I've also
got regulator I've got many users okay
well first we better identify who the
users are so we start so we'll start off
with the public and the business okay
well they have needs and hopefully the
public has a need for a cup of tea if
I'm doing a tea shop and the business
has a need to sell Cups of Tea because
that's where it's going to get its money
from all right uh so my Anor are going
to be public in business um I can put
Regulators here okay uh so what what
next and I was thinking about this when
I thought a cup of tea has needs itself
it needs a cup it needs tea and it needs
hot water and of course hot water needs
cold water needs Kettle and Kettle needs
power so what I've got is a chain of
needs this needs that and the further I
go down that chain the less visible
something becomes so if I'm a member of
the public drinking my cup of tea the
power that went into the sort of kettle
that's quite far removed from me so I've
got this notion of position through how
visible something is how and it's
described itself in the chain okay but
this is a graph I thought how do I turn
this into a
map well it turns out cuz I was looking
at this stuff and think thinking about
well cattle and power um I realized you
know power hasn't been uniform it's
changed over time well like the kettle
you know the electric kettle for example
obviously somebody in it's now a
commodity but at some point somebody
invented it so all of these components
turned out to be different forms of
capital and they all seem to be evolving
and so I did a piece of work looking
into how things evolve and I
stumbled um in the British library after
six months of working on this problem I
I had a whole bunch of data and it came
together and it just fell in place a lot
of accidents and it turned out there was
a fairly simple process by which things
evolve you start off with the Genesis of
Novel and new items then you get custom
built examples of things then you get
products and rental services and then
you get commodity and Utility Services
now these are just labels for different
stages 1 2 3 and four because it turns
out you can map things like data
knowledge ethical values all sorts of
things but what I've got now on this map
is I've got the anchor at the top
business and public I've got position
described through a chain of needs and
I've got this concept of movement or
Evolution um in terms of how evolve the
forms of uh um capital r so this was the
sort of
first map that I produced back in well
actually it was uh because I'd actually
mapped my own business so I was just
finding a way of explaining somebody
else had to do mapping so wasn't quite
the first but one of the first Maps uh
that I produced in
2005 and I was looking at this and I
realized um what I'm actually doing is
I'm exposing my assumptions about how to
make a t- shop in a way that other
people can look at those assumptions and
Challenge and question what I'm doing
because you might go why is kettling
custom Bill surely kettle's more of a
commodity you might go we're a staff uh
you might go hey we're a business we got
to take payment we're missing tills
we're missing somewhere for people to
see uh you know we to sit sorry we're
missing um you know what about cakes um
there's all sorts of things um what I'm
doing is I'm exposing my assumptions in
a way that people can see the sort of
knowledge I have around a space and they
can add to
it and something bizarre I
realized is that in most the
organizations I'd ever worked in uh we
were all very much uh story Le
organizations and in fact there's an
entire industry which tends to go around
telling people that to be a good leader
you've got to be a good
Storyteller well the problem with that
is if I give you a story and if you
challenge my story you're challenging my
ability to leave so I tend to get very
defensive but if I put my story in a
map you're not challenging me you're
telling me there's something wrong with
the map so suddenly I found a loss of
the sort of tensions which we were to
have around discussing something just
just disappeared because we we could
discuss the problem uh through the
medium of the map and I've done this
with things like uh brexit and remain in
the UK to all sorts of really thorny
issues getting quite difficult groups to
uh find ways of actually uh talking to
each other through the medium of a map
and it's it's it's not it's an old
architecture trick it's why use models
uh models of
buildings as a as a way of getting
people to to to look at and describe the
you know their feelings about things and
their assumptions about
things um so I started using these maps
and I used to go into all sorts of uh
organizations and uh I I
was working with these maps and I ended
up doing all sorts of interesting things
in government as well so this is a
friend of mine Liam Maxwell we wrote
something called the with several others
the better for Less paper Francis M
which led to a whole bunch of
transformations in UK
government um and just simply by mapping
out one particular project this was back
in about 2014 I mean they they saved
about 425 million um and they estimated
about 1.5 billion in its lifetime now
this these might s well some
ridiculously huge fig how can this
possibly be true I mean my maps have
been used to put up uh NASA and Planet
work together through through my full
mapping used it to put up the uh
interestingly carbon mapper satellite
and just to show you why this sort of
stuff uh these impact big impacts become
possible uh this is an insurance company
this was back in roughly
2011 200
12ish um this is a business process
flow um for putting servers into their
data center so they would they needed
compute they'd order a server server
would go into Goods in modify Mount
Racket and they had a bottleneck in this
process flow and so they' invested time
about six months um got various uh uh
vendors in and worked out a way using
robotics to to get rid of this bot onic
so it would accelerate the speed at
which they could you know rack service
basically and um it's quite impressive
work return of investment calculations
sub one year uh several million of
capital expenditure in terms of the
robotics they're just about to go for it
and I was asked to come and have a look
at this
problem um it was a friend of mine just
asked me to just go and have a have a
look just make sure it Mak
sense and so the problem is they' spent
six months working on the
problem um they got all their vendors
they got all their business case they
got all their calculations I mean I'm
just turning up I'm
nobody um if I challenge the story you
know it's a game over so I said
well I don't really know what you're
doing do you mind if we just map it and
they were like oh we don't don't really
want to m it and blah and I think we
spent about 20 minutes arguing about
whether we should map it and then about
15 minutes actually mapping it and so
this is the map they came up with there
we are 2010 slightly ear than I thought
user needs
compute which they yeah put in product
order server very commodity uh servers
Bly enough they thought servers were
commodity but compute was slightly less
okay it's
2010 um it's surprising only because of
cloud was 2006 uh Goods in very
commodity and then they had rat Mount
modify and I was able to look at this
map and simply go why have you got rack
and custom buil and they said oh we have
custom buil
racks ah so what are the modifications
you're making to service well the
servers don't fit into our custom build
racks so we have to take cases off Drew
new Hol ad new plates that's the
bottleneck and that's why they need
robot
and somebody in the room simply just
went why don't we use stand at
recks um now what you've got to remember
course when somebody said that
everybody's looking at them yeah why
don't we uh why are we doing all this
customization it just doesn't make any
sense at all now what you have to
remember these people aren't DED these
people are simply trapped by a
story um so at some point in the past it
made sense uh to have custom built racks
because there was no such thing as
standard racks but they never evolve
from that
point so obviously what you want to do
is evolve that
component what they'd actually been
doing all of this time is improving the
process flow so you often see these
people focusing on process flow rather
than evolutionary flow so you know they
literally do the wrong things I I mean I
had one
organization well actually I've got
another one actually this another
particular organization they were they
had weighing scales so we this
particular group had so many paper
forms um that it was actually cheaper to
weigh the number of paper forms they
used to come in palet to calculate the
number of paper forms there were than to
to manually count them and and they need
to do this to quickly report a specific
number to another group um so they
literally had weighing scales for this
and they had some mathematicians who
worked on algorithms to determine you
know how many uh how much weight went to
how many paper
fought and so simply mapped it out at
the top and of course then you look at
where the paper forms coming from Goods
in uh you go and talk to people in Goods
in and the paper forms are coming from
distribution sites all over the country
enough and they're in this sort of
digital program they want to basically
make the weighing scales connect to
their computer systems so uh uh that's
their digital
transformation but you go down to a
distribution site and ask them what are
they doing and they they've got big
printing presses because they're
printing out paper forms and you go well
where are you printing them out from So
You map that out and it turns out that
users are filling in an online website
to which they print out these forms
and then they ship them to this other
group and they don't know why they ship
them but they ship them to this other
group who then weighs the forms to work
at how many
users filled in an online website so the
entire process because no one
understands the whole picture makes no
sense whatsoever so this sort of stuff
is
typical people don't think about
evolutionary flow and one of the things
once you start doing this um you start
discovering uh you start using Maps
before we do something to do what we
call premortem challenge so before we
start act like investing in robotics
we'll map out the space and then we'll
ask ourselves you know does it make
sense we Challenge and then we'll go and
do something and then once we've done
something we do postmortem learning
using exactly the same vehicle the B and
from that we learn
Pats now there are so many patterns uh
um which there
are what we call climactic patterns
there's about 30 of these principles we
found about 40 about 100 different forms
of gameplay most people are oblivious to
all of this stuff and I've used it um
myself um so I used to run straty for a
company called Canon cor they provide
something called a buntu uh in 2008 we
were 2 to 3% of the operating system
market up against Microsoft and red had
they had all the money or everything all
the people um we had half a million
pounds and we had 18 months and we went
from 3% of the operating system Market
to 70% of all cloud computing
so um if you understand the landscape it
can have a devastating effect against
those you compete
with but this is uh James Finley good
friend he used to be the CIO for hs2
highspeed rail big heavy engineering
project and James had a problem I think
this was about
2012 um that he
um well they wanted to build a virtual
world of the Railway um because it's
cheaper to dig up a virtual world and go
whoops we've got that wrong than it is
the English Countryside So This Is A
System's graph for the system building a
virtual world of the Railway and James's
problem was he want to know how to
manage this so typically in government
in those days we used to break it into
small
contracts uh like lot one engineering
lot two user experience we group common
things into those contracts and then
would Outsource it to some supplier and
the net result was almost always the
same massive cost overruns massive
delays and this sort of stuff so so
James wanted to find a different way now
I'd been mapping from 2005 and some of
the patterns I'd learned directly
applied to this model
so um I was very fortunate in that James
had spent Sunday afternoon um creating a
map and I said well send me what your
map what you've got so this was the map
and this was in 2012 and I said well
it's quite easy now to work out how to
manage
this sort of stuff the reason why it's
quite easy is that as things evolve
their characteristics change so on the
left hand side it's very Uncharted
chaotic uncertain and on the right hand
side it's very
industrialized doesn't matter whether
it's money penis and Computing it all
evolves from that sort of genst or more
commodity and because of that we'd
learned back in
2006 uh there's no such thing as one
size fits all management methods so
things like agile extreme programming
were very good um on the left hand side
where your focus had to be about
reducing the cost of change because
change was normal uh where on the right
hand side of the map you want to be all
about reducing deviation so things like
Six Sigma outsourcing good and in the
middle of the map you want to be about
leaning off the shelf products because
you're all about learning and reducing
waste so we simply took that and you
apply it to the map and you go right
we're going to build in house with agile
techniques over here we're going to use
off-the-shelf products in the middle and
we're going to Outsource to utility
providers on the right hand side and if
we want to we can now break it into
small contracts where we bring together
things which are similar in terms of
nature of how we manage them rather than
just random grouping of words because
they sound
similar so that's what James did and
that project delivered way ahead of
schedule way under budget ended up in
front of the Public Accounts committee
um quite an exceptional
thing but one of the patterns we learned
well in this case a principle was use
appropriate methods it didn't matter
whether we were doing financing or or
project management there's no such thing
as a one-size fits all method because
the characteristics change and therefore
uh the way you treat it has to change as
well
of course there's a word of difference
between using agile like extrem
program and being agile being agile
means basically using appropriate
methods I mean if you try and use Six
Sigma across the lot you'll be good on
the right hand side you'll suffer on the
left if you try to use agile across the
lot you're good on the left and suffer
on the
right so if we go back to uh the
original contract structure and I take
one of those contracts lot one
engineering and I simply take that and
look at the mapping format so exactly
the same contract but now I'm looking at
the map I can tell you this contract is
going to fail before we even sign the
paperwork and it's going to fail because
the stuff on the right hand side might
be efficiently treated we can Define it
in a contract but the stuff on the left
hand side would always incur excessive
change control costs we've doomed out
elves by trying to Define that's which
we're still learning about
so I mean that's a gentle introduction
I'm not going to go through all the
patterns and everything else but even at
this stage I mean the most common
problems I find with business um is one
they don't actually understand their
users which of course you have to do in
order to map that's the anger secondly
they don't understand their user
needs um which is fairly terrifying
thirdly they don't understand their comp
components are the supply chain of all
the things which go into making up what
they're actually doing and I think
that's become extremely clear over the
last 10 years that so few companies
actually understand that supply chain um
but worse on that you can't just treat
every component of the same so they
don't even understand how evolved those
components are which is why we always
end up with these fads of one size fits
all let's agile everything let's six
sign or everything or whatever it
happens to be none of them work because
you have to use appropriate methods cuz
the components evolve so their
characteristics change so along with not
understanding uh users user needs not
understanding the supply chain
components not understanding how evolved
components are uh using inappropriate
methods um it turns out most
organizations that their structures are
fundamentally flawed um because then
that needs to change with the context
and they also don't have any mechanism
to effectively challenge each other
without Landing in that Dreadful world
of stories which is highly political and
so you you learn the lesson pretty
quickly you don't challenge the
executive story well we want to but
there is no mechanism to do so without
causing that
confrontation um so that i' learned
those lessons probably
about 2007
and it's just grown grown since then and
as I say there's about 30 common
economic patterns um which are useful
for anticipation it's about 40
principles like use appropriate methods
it's just one um and then you start to
learn you can manipulate the space and
there's about a 100 different forms of
gameplay so I suppose that's my as easy
as I can make it introduction into
mapping at that point I'll stop
I won't stop sharing because Daniel can
do that for me there we are
Susan was that a good enough
intro absolutely absolutely actually you
uh yeah despite I was actually in three
of your
projects what education um and and so
you despite actually being in the midst
of it um what you've showed me today is
is that it's you when we talk about
components um that may need some
clarification uh to be able to translate
that into active inference but but the
the this is also showing the
internal um representation the resource
uh utilization which is very important
in active inference we refer to that as
you free energy um and um and so it's
not just about you know what is here
what I'm trying to you know either avoid
a threat or go after an
opportunity exploration
exploitation but it's also about how I'm
I'm actually organizing or how to look
at the organization the internal
composition or
configuration in terms of that
utilization so utilization of
opportunity and how do you how do you
actually think about that so so help me
bring that home for active inference
Daniel so so there's a couple of points
I can run off that um and because I I I
love the Practical examples actually um
because that's where I sort of come from
I
um I mean we can talk about
organizational structures I I I
developed a cellbase structure which
used to be called Pioneer settlers Town
planners those words are very
problematic so these days call explorers
Villages and town planners it it it's a
uh basically a structure you break using
a map you break into small uh groups
very much explorers on the leftand side
it turns out that people have different
attitudes and work well in different
areas how they have um um also different
aptitudes so you get Explorer Engineers
explorers marketers explorers in terms
of finance and it's good to bundle those
people together um and uh what we do is
then we
introduce villages in the middle and
town planners they have different
characteristics we allow people to self-
select and then we create what's known
as a system of theft so the town plan is
still from The Villages which forces the
villages to Ste the work of the
explorers and the Explorers therefore
have to get on with exploring and this
enforces Evolution into a system so I
introduced that in all 2006 2007 there's
a wonderful paper by uh gchq which is
our intelligence Services which uh
called boiling frogs you'll see a lot of
those Concepts uh within that paper as
well I'm cited in it so um yes but um I
can talk about organization but I I
wanted to talk about the sort of value
and um the the
um how do you use U maps to ask
questions so let me just jump to
something else hang on a second um Miro
all
right so this is a
group uh they built a
system and like many groups they built a
system the system had gone live and then
somebody said you asked the question
what's the return of
investment and of course um at some
point in the past somebody created some
sort of plan which had a return
investment calculation but if you dig
into it what really happened is an
executive read an article in some
magazine or talk to a friend thought
this was a good idea we should do some
AI or
whatever um had commissioned a group
internally who then gone and talked to
another group to find out how much would
be the cost of implementing this then
then taking that figure to another group
to work out what the return investment
calculation needed to look like and
finally gone to marketing and say look
can we have some evidence to justify
building this and so the entire exercise
was an exercise um in justifying
building what the executive wanted on a
whim and that's probably normal as in
the vast majority of things go on
terrifying because there is no process
of Challenge and So eventually somebody
said you know we spent all this money on
this thing what is the
value and and there is obviously some
business case which gives a blahy blah
and of course it's
meaningless um so they asked me well how
do we work out the value of the system
so I simply said and this took two hour
in total um first of all tell me what
you think the system provides
what do we mean by you know what is the
value and so creating opportunities to
add value quickly being able to provide
synchronized environments that's
apparently what this system was doing
being user Centric okay cool out of the
box solution for developers management
of complicate all right fine so you got
a B whole bunch of words and then what
you do is I normally get them to group
those words into
themes or perspect perspectives so some
of these words were about
speed uh some of them were about cost
and value some of them about removal of
heavyweight Assurance processes some
about simplification some about
confidence in the environment now I
often do these with research groups of
you know sometimes fairly small 20 to 30
people more recently there's usually 80
or 90 people so we'll get huge amounts
of words and and also these themes as
well and then would choose a number of
themes if a small group we might just
pick one um if we have a large enough
group we can break into smaller groups
to to look at
many so in this case they pick the
removal of heavyweight Assurance
processes which was not something they'
been thinking of beforehand but
something which came up in this
discussion so we immediately went to
mapping out from the perspective of our
common platform for Assurance um and
dated
2023 uh so a couple of things maps have
no concept of time on them any more than
geographical maps have what happens is
that over time the map changes okay
secondly or maps are imperfect
representations of a space uh a perfect
map of uh France would be or Paris even
would be the size of Paris which means
as a map that's useless so all maps are
imperfect representations in order to be
useful you know but they are
representations of the landscape they
are not the
landscape um the third thing is that all
maps have a perspective so if no one had
map Paris and you sent a group of people
to map Paris and they came back and you
ask them a question like what's the most
important thing in Paris they might go
Pierre's Pizza Parlor because they
mapped it from the perspective of nice
places to eat pizza so if you want to
map space you send normally multiple
groups to map from different
perspectives and then what you can do is
aggregate those perspectives together so
you can you basically ask the same
question on each map and then you
aggregate the answers together so in
this case they built a a map with a
common Assurance uh platform they talked
about what's involved engineering teams
end users and once they hav't that we
simply ask the question you know value
assumes we going to be able to measure
something what is it that we're going to
be able to measure with this map and so
they came up with a whole bunch of
things like bugs between environments
cost per transaction time for a new
service uh decrease in negative press
stories speed of assurance approval and
once you've got those answers um you
simply say how easy are they to
implement and what's the value to the
sponsor and users and you they just put
them on here of course done in Mirror
this entire process takes about 2
hours and now they've got a whole bunch
of you know fairly easy to implement
high value things that they can actually
go and build metrics for and they had no
idea beforehand what the cost per
transaction or percent of uh policy
implemented or time to fix for bug
issues these are really simple things
which they can now go and fix let's show
you a slightly
more uh demanding
one so let me have a look agriculture
let's look at
sustainability
sustainability okay
yes um are you into sustainability or
healthc care
or what we do
sustainability so this is a slightly
larger one and this takes a long time
this took hours um which you know in
business terms is you not huge Sly
enough people
spend mons writing strategies which is
quite funny so they started off by you
know what matters in
sustainability and you get this Splurge
of words um things like modularity
energy security protecting biod
diversity great so this is the list here
apparently it all matters
um so you got to do all of this stuff
green skills middle impact on resources
loads of
things so the next thing you do is you
get people to group it into
thieves uh so the first bit takes about
an hour this bit takes about an hour so
they created a whole bunch of themes or
perspectives so policy standards and
legislation some were connected to
Circular economy some connected to
leadership in governance organizational
governments social all sorts of things
and then what they do is you self
organize into small groups and each of
those groups now goes and Maps out the
industry from a particular perspective
so this one is doing uh
sustainability uh oh that was just an
example sorry this one is doing modeling
and
complexity there's different people in
the group and Tiani and Ben have taken
the role as lead mappers and modeling
and understanding complexity
um within the sustainability field so
they start adding components and then
they usually start shifting to a tool
like online worldly maps and so they're
going through having discussion about
what components matter where they matter
Etc until they end up with what they
think is a good enough
map and the next question you ask is
well if you've got a good enough
map which is all you can ever have um
where could you invest on on the map not
where should we invest but where could
you invest so they come up with a list
of different areas that we could invest
on the map and you do that each of these
Maps um you can
see they're picking different areas
great then what you
do is you aggregate this all together
so you ask them uh a
question um so um once they pick the
different areas you ask them to
highlight in their groups what are the
most important areas
for um and it could be improving Society
or um return on investment making
money and so they the Highlight in this
case is for improving Society they've
got different ideas so you've got one
group collaborative Finance pattering
characterization one's all about
measurement and and surprisingly a
supply chain audible tool chains and
what you find is on the different Maps
similar themed areas have come up so now
you can aggregate across all the
different
maps and what you end up
with something that looks like this
so when we ask people and this it took
10 hours to get to starting from uh you
know what do we do need to do about
sustainability um it turns out and these
are all people who work in the
sustainability industry and there are
about 60 of them from all sorts of
different uh Parts turn out the things
that we really need to focus on are
Civic engagement compliance and auditing
measurement and then after that
manufacturing practices government
policies Financial now interestingly
when you ask the question or you go and
do analyst reports so you aggregate
analyst reports you tend to get the
answers on the right hand side so the
high priority is Technology Innovation
we're always in the sustainability field
investing in looking for we've been
doing it for 40 years looking for the
magic technology that will solve
sustainability problems at the same time
of course CO2 has gone up through the
roof or it's going to be financial
instruments like uh um carbon offsets
again we've been doing this for 40 years
getting nowhere um and again the
marketing messages or the markets
message is the stuff on the right and
but you see a real difference once you
once you map a landscape and ask people
to focus on from the purpose of
improving Society where would you focus
it's very different from where would you
focus in terms of making money and you
see that across so many different
Industries Healthcare
agriculture uh defense and all the rest
of it um if you look at something like
healthare oh there we
are you end up with
this so if you got a whole bunch of
doctors and nurses together and you you
get them to map out the space and
everything else and um of course they
have to break into small groups because
you only have eight people are mapping a
group at most usually so we try and
break into small groups and then you
aggregate them together what you
discover is that if we want to improve
health care uh from the focus on benefit
to society it's all about measuring of
Health outcomes auditing against prompts
patient reported outcome measures which
we don't do we measure against claros
which is clinician report outcomes so
symptoms we don't really have a health
care System we have a sick care system
we're very good at treating symptoms not
making people healthy um so we should
really focus on measurement Health
outcome sharing a medal data and that's
the list over there but if you look at
it from the market it's all about
personalized do it yourself medicine
education well-being uh industrialized
AI lot that's quite a high priority
thing where of course you know and
things like measurement of Health
outcomes right at the bottom of the list
so you often find those sorts of things
so one of the things I do the maps is um
it's not just when you want to look at a
landscape if I can I will get a large
group of people together well come up
with some general themes by asking the
question of what matters and then
consolidate it and then we'll break into
small groups like multiple sensors and
we'll go and map out the space then we
can ask each group what's important and
then we take all those answers and we
aggregate it together and this is what
gives us a signal for um what matters so
if you go back to the P example if you
sent out a dozen groups to map from
different perspectives rather than
getting Pier's pizza parlor if you
aggregated you're likely to find the
Eiffel Tower for
example point I will stop did that help
oh and Susan you did the the education
one which was always great because the
mapping exercises
themselves were always fun because the
education group had a a bunch of people
who worked in the education profession
obviously and they always started from a
focus of um uh whenever we were mapping
it was benefit to students and
opportunity and every time we map we
were forced to basically recreate the
map because there was the realization
through the process the entire education
system system doesn't work for the
benefit of students it works for the
benefit of government and social
cohesion and the educational institutes
and I mean it was the same with the the
the sort of um Healthcare everybody
thought wow Healthcare obviously is
there for the benefit of the patients if
you look at most the maps it's actually
there for the benefit of medical
institutions and pharmaceutical
companies and patients are right down
the bottom of the
list so yes we could expand that one I I
will I was also on the gaming one oh yes
what was interesting was that I think
you mentioned that that was the only one
that there was a symmetry
between what the um what was good for
culture and what was good for industry
it was a wise investment as well as that
which yeah I want to come back to
because I think this kind of pulls this
back into the
the free
energy if I look at the map for the
gaming one so um Daniel I don't know if
you've popped up the map but just to to
go through it we start off with this
huge amount of noise of stuff that
matters we going go through this process
of categorizing into themes and
generating the maps breaking into small
groups mapping out the areas identifying
on each of the maps what matters and not
actually showing you that I can show you
it it's the stuff
above oh here we are that's the all the
groups doing their work identifying
different themes and everything else and
it's even more messy than that there we
are um but basically what we end up
with if I can find where I was there we
are we end up with all this
noise and we end up with this little
table at the end
created all together and it turned out
yes you're absolutely right they quite a
light I mean and probably the only
example I've ever found uh where if you
focus on what's important to society and
if you focus what's on important in
making a return on Capital there's
pretty good alignment uh between the two
I mean obviously AI content quite high
in terms of making return on Capital but
not bad Community is quite important for
both that's slightly more important is
the highest priority for uh a benefit to
society um uh but uh it's not bad
alignment at all uh certainly healthc
care defense agriculture are way
different really
distorted well and I do want to point
out that all of this is in GitHub it's
all open source yes results of the maps
um and all free yeah and you and so that
you that uh speaks
to what you know what I'm gonna point
out what I'm what's top of mine and then
I want to hear what what Daniel has to
say but yeah specifically going back to
what you said about um the the
value versus the ease of implementation
and you know and so when you're
aggregating you collective
intelligence then that's actually giving
you predictive power in terms of where
is the likelihood things are going to
move um you and and and so the tapping
into that um the
self-organization the power in
self-organization to enable that
emergence of what is what is going to be
the the the most powerful least uh you
variational energy that we're going to
be able to mobilize so it's
mobilization um you know whether you're
you you're in the midst of it now you
know with active inference we're you
know we're talking about an ecosystem
with very very diverse um you know
different professions and and so you
they organized chaos but yeah I'm kind
of seeing some routes in how to actually
orchestrate those uh to find that you
that sweet spot what do you
thinking I I think there there is
another form of mapping which is created
by a friend of mine Dave Snowden so Dave
Snowden we meet up regularly like every
week uh and uh we were talking a few
hours ago actually uh before this this
event so um and of course Dave's taken a
sort of long interest in sort of mapping
stuff that I've done he's got a a
different way of looking at it it's um
something called esterine mapping and
that really looks at um because his
focus is on you know if we've got a
whole range of things we can do what are
the things which are within the realm of
what we can possibly do what what what
in terms of energy input in terms of
time uh becomes uh possible and so he's
got some really interesting stuff about
history mapping I mean there
are there are very few forms of mapping
that I'm aware of there's another one
called uh Burger mapping which is really
interesting if you're looking at
stakeholders and political play in
organization there's EST mapping as well
and then there's my former wle Maps
which um you know this this stuff is
almost 20 years old now ridiculous but
uh and this stuff by the way is all
creative comments
so it's interesting because once you
create a map of a space and you've ID Ed
the map to identify where you could
invest and then you
aggregate um to see in this case we're
aggregating them in terms of what should
we what is a high priority this isn't
actually answering the
question uh can we actually do this so
um if you go back to the if I go back to
the value one
um so that
was not education gaming let's have a
look um no I don't want to open that
one just common
develop here you've got um where
actually having identified different
areas we're now asking that question of
ease to implement versus um uh value to
the sponsor so this is the point where
you know you use the map to identify
different areas and um you're now asking
you know these are things we could
easily change this helped you make that
decision on what you should change I
think EST mapping is a better form of
doing that a bit here I mean I would use
the maps to try and understand the
landscape as much as possible and use
the maps to sort of my form maps to
identify the areas you could change help
you develop the questions U but then in
days form uh which which is EST mapping
which is not this um really asked that
question about the energy and the time I
think that's a really interesting way of
looking at the
problem yeah and and uh yeah compare
that to the typical cost benefit
analysis oh God no which it's like you
may as well use a SWAT
diagram
um okay I remember I've been doing this
for 20 years so I mean I see well it's
almost 20 years I the insurance example
is typical example that I will see a
group of people who've spent six months
working on a problem with no actual
understanding of the landscape and and
they've come up with a plan to invest
Millions into Robotics and uh they've
got all the business case all the
calculations all the vendors they've had
in they've done all their due diligence
the whole thing's ready to go um and
Beyond once we got over the 20 minutes
of arguing it took 15 minutes of mapping
and about five or 10 minutes of
discussing the map to realize the entire
thing was a waste of time that is
incredibly common I um you know look
before you leap I am always stunned um
it's a constant source of marry of
amusement um how many people make
decision iions without um understanding
the landscape and I do get myself into
hot water so I I better warn your
listeners um mapping will tend to get
you
fired the the reason being is that
whilst I say it is possible you know to
to once you understand a landscape and
you can challenge and ask questions and
all the rest of it um you do get you
know you do get these moments where you
you map out the environment and you
realize the entire strategy of the
company is to walk the people off the
edge of a cliff and you want to point
out that's really bad but it is really
it's something the executive have been
totally sold on uh and so they people
get you know despite the fact they can
see it clearly in front of them now it's
almost they go into a sense of denial
and and the solution is obviously you're
a troublemaker so I've seen loads and
loads of people uh well well not loads
quite a few people get fired as a result
of of mapping pointing out the insanity
of something that is actually actually
going on so I have to give you a a big
healthy warning uh there but on a
personal note I I have
seen I've seen so many projects and I
have got myself in trouble um I had one
particular project uh they' asked me
over to the US and I was sitting in this
boardroom and uh this was about
10 and they taken me through their
$1.2
billion plan to build a private
cloud and I'd map this out during this
meeting at the end I'd turn around and
uh I said I can build the entire lot for
you with the same effect the 25 million
and they were like how is that possible
How would you do that and I say it's
very simple you pay me 25 million I will
sit on a beach for 5 years drinking
margaritas then you phone me up and I
will say we failed and that way you'll
save all the rest of the money now this
went down like a balloon I immedately
got kicked out of the
meeting all that sort of stuff it's
spectacular um but what I what I most
remember about this story is is about
seven years later sex phoned me up and
basically said we wish we paid you 25
million um of course I've wished they'd
pay me 25 million as well but um this
stuff is frighteningly common I'm afraid
um I think that's actually where we can
help because what you just said is what
we're
modeling it's called belief
updating and so just look instead of
instead of
um focusing on behaviors yeah we're
we're actually looking at the
justifications um and it's quite
revealing so well that that that that
that's entirely different threat and um
and leads into I should say an entirely
different thread um which is the whole
sort of because you can map culture as
well I mean I I get into to um so I keep
a lot of my maps on GitHub uh they're
easy to find there's a wly mapping or
repulser there's a tool called online W
bats you can just take the code and
throw it in there again this is all
Creative Commons open some stuff you
just help yourself um but I also um do a
lot of mapping of uh different
environments so if you think about uh
the concept of Defense so mapping out
the defense space
um there are multiple
Landscapes uh on which sovereignty has a
meaning uh the one that most people know
about is territorial sovereignty So This
Is Our Land um but there's also economic
sovereignty uh technological sovereignty
uh social sovereignty and political
sovereignty and they're all important
Landscapes which you can map now most
countries I say most not all are the
same should we say um do a reasonably
good job of
territorial uh and and pretty poor job
of economic actually understanding their
economic landscape very few actually
understand their supply chains uh
there's a wonderful piece of work on in
Hungary which was looking at um a used
vat records sales tax records to to
basically graph out not even map but
graph out the uh Hungarian economic
system and of course they discover that
around with these check points with
these companies within there it's pretty
terrifying it was a very small number of
companies which if they failed would
take out 25% of the GDP of the entire
country just like
terrifying um um but but of course most
people are oblivious to this and of
course technological I mean we're now
finally talking about spawns but these
are just graphs I say that's software
building materials but they're not even
maps of the space so we still don't maps
of our technological landscape and
political and cultural I mean most
people of nowhere I mean
um and and political I should say social
and of course that's matters from the
point of view of um sovereignty I mean
uh you know if we cut back on foreign
office Aid and all this sort of stuff we
have to buy more bullets the two the two
are not um independent they are
correlated what you do in one landscape
can affect other landscape so if you you
decline you reduce soft power um you
might have to exert more kinetic force
in a in a
territorial um but this this whole sort
of area led me to um
discussions uh where it was looking at
how to map
culture and that was fascinating um
mostly because when I looked into
culture I was thinking culture I mean
what you know it's a really simple
concept foolish foolish man that I was H
and I I found um I think it was kobber
he basically said anthropologists who
are the experts on culture being arguing
over what culture means uh for over 150
years or something it was a ridiculous
length of time uh and of course there
was no actual agreement on what culture
meant which was for me quite
shocking and
um yeah this one
do and then I came across a really
really wonderful Anthropologist Margaret
me really incredible stuff and um one of
the statements of Margaret me was that
um language was part of culture and
that's interesting because if language
is part of culture um and we we we
therefore probably can't describe
culture in terms of language uh that's
something called G girdles in
completeness theorem so no no model can
be true and complete within itself so
language is part of it we've got to find
a different way so what I started doing
was well can we map out cultural
systems um so when I use a map I better
just show you a couple of bits
the the AIS at the bottom I always say
Genesis custom product commodity uh when
I'm looking at activities but this
really you should say stage one two and
three and four but you know that doesn't
mean anything to anybody and this piece
of work came from a a whole bunch of um
text analysis of
9,7 30 no
9,231 documents back in 2005 2006 very
manual process back
then and it turns out there's these
different stages and they have different
labels um different characteristics as
well so the different labels are when we
talk about practices novel emerging good
best data model Divergent convergent
model knowledge concept hypothesis
Theory and then something comes
accept and I can pick any label from
stage one and mix it with stage two and
three and four so I started mapping out
things like ethical values so looking at
you know was it a concept was it an
emerging concept was it sort of
converging was it accepted so he's doing
a lot of stuff on um sexual identity and
mapping out in that space as well uh so
when you look
at turns out you start looking at a
collective and you will'll have various
beliefs in a collective it might be
Universal basic income paid holiday
unionization uh and those beliefs
themselves will have different stages of
evolution and they'll be based upon um
underlying concept workers rights
anti-discrimination civil rights both of
those extend from the abolition of
slavery and underneath that are Concepts
like reciprocity and fairness um so you
you can see how these you know these
components themselves have evolved we
have a fairly good idea or used to I
should say a fairly good idea of
Concepts like reciprocity um that's
being a little bit challenged at the
moment but if you take this this map and
you just say well Okay so we've got some
values
beliefs and we start off with this point
here can you I don't know if you can see
my mouth
um it's values in the middle
okay so what I did was I I had a blank
map with Concept em merging converging
accepted at the bottom and charted
industrialize and put values as you know
there's this map of values in the middle
put that as a square box and then I got
a group of people who couldn't agree on
anything uh these were brexiteers and
remainers in the UK brexiteers were like
leave Europe remainers wanted to remain
and these group were incredibly hostile
to each other so if the brexiteers said
we'll have a cup of tea the remainers
would go will'll having coffee and if
the Romanians won't well have Biscuit
the brexiteers would go nowhere not
having biscuits for cake I mean these
people would just not agree on anything
whatsoever um so I had them in the room
and I said well look I'm trying to
explore the concept of culture and I
know I can't do it through the use of a
word or words alone so I've got this
concept of values and that's a that's a
map itself and I've put that in the
midle I want to think about what are the
components that make up
culture and they were a bble to discuss
this rather complicated issue and Le
through the meeting the map and this is
where they end up with so at the very
top the anchors or we and me we're all a
bit we we're all a bit me as the
individual and Collective uh the we is
all about control of the environment me
is all about individuality which is
about agency which is connected to
Concepts like power and control of
course is uh you know connected to the
collectives that we belong to we belong
to many forms of collectives and all
collectives want to succeed in the
spread of their values a church a
football club a family or whatever you
know they all want to
succeed um and of course our behaviors
are a combination of the values that we
have and the doctrine or the principles
we apply so for
example um a principle is focus on user
needs well that sounds good but but if
your belief is that people with blue
eyes and blonde hair are somehow better
than everybody else then the behavior
are focusing on user needs and the
belief that blonde blue-eyed people are
somehow Superior is not a very appealing
behavior um but um then you get into
concepts of safety which depends upon
behavior and sense of belonging which
depends upon behavior and so you start
getting Cycles within this and you can
actually use this to to form groups also
destabilize groups as well because you
that's one of the things you do with can
do with maps as well but that's how I
many many moons ago gosh this must be
about eight years ago um I got into
mapping or maybe less seven years ago uh
mapping into cultural systems and this
turns out to be a a a very imperfect but
interesting definition of culture so
when I say when people say what is
culture I go well that's culture and um
my particular interest and the reason
why we did the video gaming one is
because if you want to change the
behaviors of a collective well the
principles are are universally useful
principles so as long as people are
aware of and there's a list of about 40
of those what we need to really do is
change the values and the beliefs and
one of the ways of doing that is through
memory
so symbols rituals and heroes um or in
other words art art is one of the most
powerful forces there is to changing the
values and beliefs in are collected and
the single largest form of art today is
immersive video games which is why we
were doing that research project because
I have a particular interest if we want
to change the behaviors of you know
National collectives um probably the
best way of attacking the problem is
through andless of video
games that all makes
sense yeah thank you I mean there
there's so many places to jump in but I
want to respect your time
perhaps we can close the session there
and then Susan and I could stay for a
few minutes and read some of the
thoughts that we had about active
inference oh my apologies I didn't see
what the time
was oh sorry I talked for far too long I
I have a terrible habit I can do this
for days
um I hope I hav B your rigid
um you said what you wanted to
say oh no was fantastic fantastic and I
feel would you like to continue a bit
longer or I can just mention a few of
the points that Susan and I had like
thought about and prepared just more to
footnote it for just thinking about it
more in everyone's own time um yeah
there there's so much here that uh that
you there is so many different
crossovers between uh these these two
directions yeah and uh and and so you
that I mean I've got so many but I'm GNA
let turn it over to uh to Daniel to kind
of pull these thread it all together so
we can um mine this uh the Brilliance
this is just going to be reading from
the document that we already prepared so
not just to connect and and notes being
taken so it's not in any order this
isn't any specific synthesis um but the
the the ideas of cognitive mapping
worldly mapping as a cognitive activity
strategy or behavior being separated
from the landscape this is like the
agent on the niche the phone
distribution and the nestmate and the
pherone distribution can't be changed
instantly that's actually something
happening that's separate from the
control of like any navigation path and
landscape and so being able to have real
specific practices and all of this
fractal diversity and practices as well
just like there's Tools in a workshop in
the path finding wayf finding
areas this is mapping technique and then
underneath cardgraphic technique is
cardgraphic research and measurement and
Signal processing control theory all
these other areas um however more
specification or formalization is not
always the rate limiting step or the
step that's aligned with any particular
outcome that's kind of like the
recognition that actually I think just
from what I have heard helps the
participation go beyond just sourcing
information and words like if you just
wanted all the words you could download
a dictionary but there's actually
something in the process and the the
time and the attention as that feeds
back upon itself that is is
qualitatively different than just like
the Playbook the playbook in the kitchen
you know is different from the
restaurant changing through time so like
that those are just kind of General then
just a little bit more on the specifics
with active inference really interesting
how this is like a snapshot shot that
has position and then a first derivative
or second derivative like how how fast
is it changing what Vector is it
changing in how fast is that changing
that could be taken very far formally
with active inference that's basically
basian mechanics then separation of
consideration with the UDA Loop and the
connection to the principles also
previously we've connected the UDA
functions and cycle to action perception
basically describing the same territory
they're different Maps so having a PL
ISM of approaches and actually mapping
them at a higher level like systems
engineering Maps or active inference
ecosystems of shared intelligence
complex systems all these being
recognized as Maps helps have the
epistemic humility and the pluralism and
it's also like arguably a correct
formalism that takes mapping to like its
logical completeness as a method of
pragmatic inquiry and then um separation
of of the sense making of the
landscape from the actions that can be
taken and then in active inference like
the equations have all those kinds of
considerations like how the world States
change through time that the perceptions
the actions the affordances like all
these different terms um however that
equation is very um silent on how to do
it procedurally through time with a
group obviously the equation could be
used in in every single possible way so
even if like this were more
accurate that you could make a decision
with this or that consequence on this
map or you could have chosen the other
way on a different one and so then that
brings in some really
interesting considerations of inquiry
which I think just to kind of conclude
speaks to the different ways that some
of the theory of cognitive systems and
all of like the connections that people
will see who study the formalisms in act
dim that theory and how that
remarkable seeing what people you know
think and how they get involved so thank
you bye Awesome by bye